In 1991 I had
في عام 1991 كانت لي تجربة
maybe the most profound and transformative
ربما الأكثر عمقا وتحويلا
experience of my life.
في مجرى حياتي.
I was in the third year of my seven-year undergraduate degree.
كنت في السنة الثالثة من دراستي الجامعية التي تتواصل لسبع سنوات.
I took a couple victory laps in there.
فقد عشت فترات من النجاح هناك.
And I was on a college choir tour up in Northern California,
وكنت في جولة جوقة تابعة للكلية شمال كاليفورنيا،
and we had stopped for the day after all day on the bus,
ويوما ما، توقّفنا بعد السّفر يوما كاملا على متن الحافلة،
and we were relaxing next to this beautiful
وحاولنا الاسترخاء بجوار هذه
idyllic lake in the mountains.
البحيرة الجبليّة الجميلة.
And there were crickets and birds and frogs making noise,
وكانت هناك الصراصير والطيور والضفادع تصدر أصواتا،
and as we sat there, over the mountains coming in
وجلسنا هناك، فوق الجبال بالجهة
from the north were these Steven Spielbergian clouds
الشماليّة حيث كانت هناك غيوم تشبه ستيفن سبيلبرغ
rolling toward us,
تتجّه نحونا،
and as the clouds got about halfway over the valley,
وعند وصول الغيوم بمنتصف طريقها نحو الوادي،
so help me God, every single animal in that place
كلّ حيوان في ذلك المكان
stopped making noise at the same time.
توقّف عن اصدار أصوات في نفس الوقت.
(Whoosh) This electric hush, as if they could sense what was about to happen.
هذا الصمت الكهربائي، كما لو أنّها عرفت ما كان على وشك أن يحدث.
And then the clouds came over us, and then,
ثم جاء الغيوم فوق رؤوسنا، ومن ثم،
boom! This massive thunderclap, and sheets of rain.
بوم! قصف رعد قويّ، وهطل المطر بغزارة.
It was just extraordinary, and when I came back home
كان الأمر مذهلا، وعندما رجعت إلى المنزل
I found a poem by the Mexican poet Octavio Paz,
وجدت قصيدة للشاعر المكسيكي أوكتافيو باث،
and decided to set it to music,
وقرّرت أن أقوم بتلحينها،
a piece for choir called "Cloudburst,"
لمقطوعة جوقة سمّيتها "العاصفة"،
which is the piece that we'll perform for you in just a moment.
وهي المقطوعة التي سنقوم بأداءها قريبا.
Now fast forward to just three years ago.
الآن ننتقل بالزّمن إلى 3 سنين مضت.
(Music) And we released to YouTube this,
(موسيقى) نشرنا هذا على اليوتيوب،
the Virtual Choir Project,
مشروع الجوقة الافتراضيّة،
185 singers from 12 different countries.
185 مغنّيا من 12 بلدا مختلفاً.
You can see my little video there conducting these people,
يمكنكم مشاهدتي في هذا الفيديو أقود هؤلاء النّاس،
alone in their dorm rooms
الجالسون بمفردهم في غرف نومهم
or in their living rooms at home.
أو غرف المعيشة بالمنزل.
Two years ago, on this very stage, we premiered
قبل عامين، في هذه نفس هذا المسرح، بدأنا
Virtual Choir 2,
الجوقة الافتراضيّة 2،
2,052 singers from 58 different countries,
بمساعدة 2052 مطربا من 58 بلدا مختلفاً،
this time performing a piece that I had written called "Sleep."
وتلك المرّة عرضنا مقطوعة من تأليفي اسمها "نوم".
And then just last spring we released Virtual Choir 3,
وثم في الربيع الماضي فقط نشرنا الجوقة الافتراضيّة 3،
"Water Night," another piece that I had written,
"ليلة المياه،" مقطوعة أخرى من تأليفي،
this time nearly 4,000 singers from 73 different countries.
وهذه المرة جمعنا 4000 مغنّيا من 73 بلدا مختلفاً.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And when I was speaking to Chris about the future
وعندما كنت أتحدّث مع كريس حول مستقبل
of Virtual Choir and where we might be able to take this,
الجوقة الافتراضية، وإلى أيّ مدى يمكننا الوصول،
he challenged me to push the technology as far as we possibly could.
تحدّاني لدفع التكنولوجيا إلى أقصى ما يمكن.
Could we do this all in real time?
هل يمكننا القيام بذلك في الآن؟
Could we have people singing together in real time?
هل نستطيع جعل الناس تغنّي معا في نفس الوقت؟
And with the help of Skype,
بمساعدة سكايب،
that is what we are going to attempt today.
هذا ما نحن بصدد محاولة القيام به اليوم.
Now, we'll perform "Cloudburst" for you.
الآن، سوف نغنّي لكم "العاصفة".
The first half will be performed by the live singers here on stage.
النصف الأول سيؤدّيه مطربون موجودون هنا على خشبة المسرح.
I'm joined by singers from Cal State Long Beach,
وهم مطربون من جامعة كاليفورنيا بلونغ بيتش،
Cal State Fullerton and Riverside Community College,
من جامعة كاليفورنيا بفولرتون كال الدولة وكلية المجتمع ريفرسايد،
some of the best amateur choirs in the country, and —
هم من من أفضل الجوقات الهواة في البلد، و —
(Applause) --
(تصفيق) --
and in the second half of the piece,
وفي النصف الثاني من المقطوعة،
the virtual choir will join us, 30 different singers
سوف ينضم إلينا 30 مغنّيا مختلفا
from 30 different countries.
من 30 بلدا مختلفاً.
Now, we've pushed the technology as far as it can go,
لقد قمت باستغلال التكنولوجيا بأقصى حدّ،
but there's still less than a second of latency,
ولكن لا يزال هناك تأخّر أقلّ من الثانية،
but in musical terms, that's a lifetime.
لكن من الناحية الموسيقية، هذه مدّة طويلة.
We deal in milliseconds.
ونحن نتعامل بالميلي ثانية.
So what I've done is, I've adapted "Cloudburst"
لذلك ما قمت به كان تكييف "العاصفة"
so that it embraces the latency
لكي لا يكون هناك تأخير
and the performers sing into the latency
وسيغنيّ المطربون دون تأخير
instead of trying to be exactly together.
بدلاً من محاولة الغناء معا.
So with deep humility, and for your approval,
ذلك وبتواضع عميق، وبعد إذنكم،
we present "Cloudburst."
نقدّم لكم "العاصفة".
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Piano)
(البيانو)
[The rain ...]
[المطر...]
[Eyes of shadow-water]
[عيون المياه المظلمة]
[eyes of well-water]
[عيون آبار المياه]
[eyes of dream-water.]
[عيون المياه الحلم.]
[Blue suns, green whirlwinds,]
[شموس زرقاء، طواحين خضراء،]
[birdbeaks of light pecking open]
[تنفتح مناقير الطّيور في الضوء]
[pomegranate stars.]
[نجوم من رمّان].
[But tell me, burnt earth, is there no water?]
[ولكن قلي لي أيّتها الأرض المحترقة، أما من مياه؟]
[Only blood, only dust,]
[فقط الدم، فقط غبار،]
[only naked footsteps on the thorns?]
[فقط خطى عارية على الأشواك؟]
[The rain awakens...]
[المطر ينهال...]
[We must sleep with open eyes,]
[يجب أن ننام بعيون مفتوحة،]
[we must dream with our hands,]
[يجب أن نحلم بأيدينا،]
[we must dream the dreams of a river seeking its course,]
[يجب أن نحلم أحلام نهر يسعى إلى مجراه،]
[of the sun dreaming its worlds.]
[وبالشمس تحلم بالأكوان].
[We must dream aloud,]
[يجب أن نحلم بصوت عال،]
[we must sing till the song puts forth roots,]
[يجب أن نغنّي حتّى تطرح الأغنية جذورها،]
[trunk, branches, birds, stars.]
[الجذع، الفروع والطيور والنجوم.]
[We must find the lost word,]
[يجب أن نجد الكلمة المفقودة،]
[and remember what the blood,]
[ونتذكّر ما يقوله الدم،]
[the tides, the earth, and the body say,]
[و المد والجزر والأرض والجسم،]
[and return to the point of departure...]
[ثمّ نعود إلى نقطة الانطلاق...]
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
["Cloudburst" Octavio Paz][translation by Lysander Kemp, adapted by Eric Whitacre]
["العاصفة" لأوكتافيو باث][ترجمها لسندار كيمب، لحّنها إيريك ويتآكر]
Eric Whitacre: Beth. Annabelle, where are you? Jacob.
إريك ويتآكر: بيث. أنابيل، أين أنتما؟ يعقوب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.